T-Those chocolates…
其實…
T-They're the ones that…
那些是做得…
t-turned out best.
最成功的巧克力
Aw, you didn't have to. Thank you very much!
妳不用特地這麼做的，謝謝妳！
POOF
（害羞）
DASH
（奔跑）
K-Komi?!
古見同學？
REALIZATION
（倏然發覺）
BALL
（縮成一團）
Shoko!
硝子！
It's time to go, isn't it?
妳差不多該出門了吧？
What's wrong? Not feeling well?
妳怎麼了？身體不舒服嗎？
Steamed bun?
肉包子？
You don't like the cold?
妳很冷嗎？
Did something happen at school yesterday?
昨天在學校發生什麼事了嗎？
SHE COULD GUESS.
（察覺到了某件事）
SHAKE SHAKE
（搖頭）
-Shoko! Go to school! -PULL
-硝子，快點去上學吧！ -（拉）
You won't get the perfect attendance award at this rate!
妳今天請假的話就拿不到全勤獎囉！
You don't mind?
沒關係嗎？
She came out.
出來了
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
Bear in mind,
不過需要注意的是
they only struggle to form connections.
這些人只是不擅長社交
It doesn't mean they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
Hey, good morning!
嗨，早安！
Thanks for the chocolate yesterday. It was good!
謝謝妳昨天送的巧克力，很好吃喔！
-YOURS WAS GOOD TOO. -Thank you!
-（尾根峰同學的也很好吃） -謝啦！
But mine were baked. You don't have to eat them all at once.
不過那些都是烤糕點 用不著勉強自己，全都一口氣吃完
You got a lot of chocolate didn't you?
妳應該收到了不少巧克力吧？
You'll gain weight.
會發胖喔
STARTLE
（驚嚇）
Hey-ho!
早安，哈囉！
Your chocolate was good!
古見同學 妳送的巧克力很好吃喔！
-A sweet offering made by my sworn ally. -WAS WAITING FOR KOMI.
-盟友製作的甜蜜貢品 -（在等古見同學經過）
It wasn't bad.
味道還算不錯
K-Komi!
古見同學！
T-The chocolate was v-very good!
妳送的巧克力超好吃的！
Komi's chocolate had a higher cacao content on the outside,
古見同學做的巧克力 外層刻意用了含量較高的可可粉
and a sweeter one inside…
和內部的生巧克力 甜味達到完美融合…
I… I lost!
我輸了！
-You lose. -MAKERU'S CHOCOLATE, KOMI'S CHOCOLATE
-妳輸了！ -（真華留的，古見的）
SLIDE
（退後）
What's wrong, Komi?
妳怎麼了？古見同學
Good morning, Komi.
早安，古見同學
PRESSURE
（隆隆聲）
Uh, huh?
什麼？那個…
Why…
妳怎麼了…
CREAK
（僵硬）
Uh, never mind.
不，沒事
I feel like I haven't seen that face in a while!
感覺很久沒看到古見同學這個表情了
Tadano didn't dislike the face she was making.
只野同學覺得這種感覺還不賴
But what's wrong, I wonder?
可是她到底怎麼了啊？
She doesn't seem angry…
看起來也不像在生氣…
Maybe because I ran after her yesterday?
難道是因為我昨天追著她跑？
Or maybe I said something weird.
還是我說了什麼奇怪的話？
There's also a good chance it's not about me to begin with.
不對，歸根究柢 原因極有可能不是出在我身上
TRYING NOT TO LOOK EMBARRASSED
（努力不讓害羞表露在臉上）
Oh yeah. I should comment on the chocolate.
對了，先跟她說巧克力的感想好了
Oh, yeah. The chocolate.
話說回來，妳給我的巧克力
It was very good.
非常好吃喔！
Thanks for that yesterday.
謝謝妳昨天特地送來
-SLAM -Komi?!
-（碰撞） -古見同學？
MISSION 71 "IT'S JUST RIPPED TIGHTS."
（任務71 綻線了）
Okay, return your instruments.
好，大家把實驗器材拿來歸還
Yes ma'am.
好
Hi! Ren Yamai here!
嗨！大家好，我是山井戀！
As always, I've got the seat with the best view of Komi's legs!
我今天坐的位子也能以最佳角度 欣賞古見同學可愛又美麗的玉腿
As always, she's godlike in her beauty.
今天古見同學的 美麗程度依然是神明等級
You're dazzling, Komi.
妳太耀眼了，古見同學
The energy from her light causes the moisture in my eyes to evaporate.
妳的光芒所釋放出來的熱能 能讓我眼裡的水分蒸發
Or perhaps it solidifies the protein.
甚至可能會讓蛋白質凝固呢
Oh! A rip!
天啊！綻線了！
N-No! Komi looks scandalous!
不行！古見同學的這種糗態
I… I have to take a video!
得馬上錄下來才行！
Just for me!
成為我的專屬收藏！
No! I can't let the rest of the class see!
不行！絕不能讓班上的人 看到她這個樣子！
For now, you can hide in my shadow, Komi!
總之先躲到我庇蔭之下，古見同學！
I've got to hide it naturally, so nobody notices!
要擋得自然一點，不能被大家發現！
Naturally!
自然地！
Y-Yamai?
山井同學？
If I tell it to her straight,
要是將這件事誠實地告訴古見同學
Komi will surely be embarrassed!
她一定會覺得很難為情！
But if I don't, she'll be more embarrassed later!
可是現在不跟她說 等她回去後會更難為情！
I'll protect her on the way home too!
當然我一定會死守到她回家為止！
What should I…
我該怎麼辦才好？
No, Ren Yamai!
不可以，山井戀！
You were trying to touch the rip!
妳剛剛居然想去觸摸 古見同學褲襪綻線的地方！
Y-You were subconsciously trying to spread open the rip!
還下意識地想去撐開那個洞！
I want to tear it.
好想撕破
-I want to tear Komi's tights to shreds. -Um…
-我好想把古見同學的褲襪撕爛 -那個…
I want to see Komi in disarray!
好想看古見同學穿破洞褲襪的樣子！
-But no! -Yamai?
-但是不可以！ -山井同學？
-Um… -No, Ren Yamai!
-那個… -妳絕對不可以這麼做，山井戀！
-I've got it! -Huh?
-有了！ -什麼？
Komi.
古見同學
Komi, there's a rip in the left thigh of your tights.
妳左大腿那邊的褲襪綻線了
It's alright. Don't worry.
沒事的，妳不用擔心
I have some 80 denier tights in the brand you use.
古見同學平常穿的那一牌80丹尼褲襪
I always carry them with me.
我都隨身攜帶著
SLIDE
（拿出）
Let's get changed in the restroom!
來，我們去洗手間換吧！
-Let's go! -Huh?
-就這麼辦吧！ -什麼？
Did the rip spread? Is it okay?
綻線處有變大嗎？還好嗎？
I'm sorry.
對不起
I should have told you sooner.
如果我再早點告訴妳就好了
I was worried you'd be embarrassed.
因為我怕妳會覺得很難為情
It's even more embarrassing if everyone sees. I'm sorry.
但要是被大家看到 會讓妳更害羞吧？對不起
I'M GLAD YOU TOLD ME.
（幸好有妳跟我說）
Komi.
古見同學
Oh, here.
對了，那這個給妳
I'll hold your old ones.
換下來的那件我幫妳拿著
W-What is happening?
這是什麼情況？
S-Should I catch her?
我該去幫忙抓人嗎？
KOMI
（古見同學）
BARE LEGS
（裸腿）
He got a good look.
他仔細盯著看
MISSION 72 "IT'S JUST AN ONI AND HER CLUB."
（任務72 如虎添翼）
Akako Onigashima.
鬼島朱子
She belongs to Yamai's group.
她隸屬於山井同學的小團體
And she's friends with Komi.
同時也是古見同學的朋友
She's friendly and cheerful.
總是笑容可掬，活力充沛
She's nice and well-liked by others.
個性也很好，大家都很喜歡她
Oh! It's Tadano!
啊，是只野同學！
Good morning!
早安啊！
Oh, Onigashima. Good morning.
啊，鬼島同學，早安
Sorry, I'm in a hurry. Bye!
抱歉，我在趕時間，先走囉！
Full of energy again today.
她今天也好有活力
She even greets Tadano with a smile.
連遇到只野同學都會笑著打招呼
She's a very nice girl. I like her.
是個非常善良的好孩子，我喜歡她
But even the girl ranked as the number one "person I wish I grew up with"…
在“想要有這樣的兒時玩伴” 排名中位居榜首的她…
Huh?
怎麼了？
…loses her temper sometimes.
也會有發飆的時候
IRRITATED
（焦躁）
-She turns into a demon when she's angry. -Tsk.
-鬼島同學一發怒就會變魔鬼… -可惡
You didn't hear it from me.
沒事，當我沒說
Why are all the lights red?
煩死了，為什麼全都是紅燈？
Alright.
終於能過了
CAN'T GET PAST THIS GUY
（鬼島同學跟前方路人 走同一邊，無法通過）
-She's waiting again. -RUMBLE
-她又在等紅燈了 -（隆隆聲）
And her earphones are tangled!
而且耳機線還纏住了！
UNRAVEL
（鬆開）
TIE
（綁）
-TIE -HARD KNOT
（綁緊 打死結）
Yamai is here!
山井同學在那邊！
Oh good.
太好了
They're good friends, so Onigashima's temper will…
她們感情這麼好，鬼島同學見到 山井同學應該就會冷靜下來…
IGNORES
（撇開）
W-Why did you turn away?
妳剛剛幹嘛把頭撇開啊？
Tadano. When did you get here?
什麼？只野同學，你在啊？
I turned away? Oh.
我把頭撇開？因為啊
I've known her for a long time.
我跟她認識很久了
We've been classmates since grade school.
我們從國小就玩在一起 所以我非常清楚
She's unpredictable when she loses her temper.
她一旦發起飆來 會做出什麼事根本無法預測
She only relieves stress by eating, bathing, sleeping, and batting.
她消除壓力的方法只有 吃飯、洗澡、睡覺和去棒球打擊場
Watch out for her.
只野同學，你自己也要小心點
Let sleeping dogs lie, as they say.
沒事千萬別去招惹她
Yamai is talking sense!
山井同學居然說出了這麼正經的話！
GROWL
（隆隆聲）
Her earphones are still tangled.
她的耳機線又纏在一起了
BOUNCE
（打到）
DEMON METER TRANSFORMS WHEN FULL
（“魔鬼量表” 一到頂點就會變魔鬼）
RUMBLE
（隆隆聲）
RIPS
（破掉）
BEEP BEEP
（嗶嗶聲）
Bread!
麵包！
It's finally lunchtime.
終於到午休時間了
Once she eats, she'll calm down.
吃完飯她應該就會稍微冷靜了
-ORANGE JUICE -SLURP
（柳橙汁 啜飲）
BEW BEW
（下降）
DROP
（滴落）
-BANG -BEEP BEEP
（砰 嗶嗶聲）
RUNS AWAY SWIFTLY
（迅速逃離）
STOMP STOMP
（腳步沉重）
Oh, thank you, Komi.
謝謝妳，古見同學
Komi?
古見同學？
IT'S TANGLED, NOT TIED, RIGHT?
（這不是刻意綁好的 而是纏在一起沒錯吧？）
WIND WIND
（繞圈）
TEARS
（落淚）
-Komi! -I SHOULDN'T HAVE UNTANGLED THEM?!
-古見同學！ -（不可以解開嗎？）
Komi!
古見同學！
Let's go to the batting center together.
我們一起去棒球打擊場吧
BATTING CENTER
（科米樂園 棒球打擊場）
The batting center!
來到棒球打擊場囉！
Tadano! I'm going to hit a home run! Watch!
只野同學！我要打出全壘打了 你仔細看清楚！
MISS
（揮棒落空）
CLUNK
（咚）
-You hit it! -MM-HM
-打中了！ -（得意）
-HIT -Tadano, average!
-（打中） -只野同學好普通！
Onigashima's good!
鬼島同學好厲害啊！
-HOME RUN -SLAM
（全壘打 碰撞聲）
-Komi, did you see? A home run! -GRIN
-古見同學看到了嗎？全壘打耶！ -（燦笑）
NOD
（點頭）
-Pretty good, hey? -Onigashima and Komi are friends.
-很厲害吧？ -鬼島同學和古見同學是朋友
MISSION 73 "IT'S JUST A PUSHOVER."
（任務73 是老好人）
SQUEAK
（擦拭）
Grade 1, Class 1. Amami Sato.
一年一班，左藤甘美
She's Komi's classmate and sits in the seat to the left.
她是從正面看 坐在古見同學左邊的同班同學
CLEAN
（清潔溜溜）
Alright.
好了
Now everyone can focus on their studies for another day.
這樣大家今天也能舒舒服服地上課了
Sato is a pushover.
左藤同學是個老好人
Look at the time!
天啊，已經這個時間了！
-RATTLE -CLACK
（開門 砰噹）
She should have the joy of being first to class.
得讓她有第一個 進教室的爽快心情才行
Sato is a pushover.
左藤同學是個老好人
Sorry, Sato. Pick up my pencil?
不好意思，左藤同學 可以幫我撿一下自動鉛筆嗎？
Oh, sure.
好，沒問題
Sato is a push--
左藤同學是個老好…
Sato!
左藤！
-Get me a limited edition chicken burger! -Sure.
-去福利社幫我買限量的雞排堡 -好啊
Sato is a…
左藤同學是個老…
-Sato, sorry. Scratch my back! -Sure.
-左藤，抱歉，可以幫我抓個背嗎？ -好啊
Sato is…
左藤同學是個…
-Sure! -Huh?
-什麼？
I haven't said…
我什麼都還沒說
SOCIAL AND CULTURAL RESEARCH CLUB
（社會民族研究社）
Do you think…
我是不是…
I do too much for people?
太常答應別人的請求了？
-You're asking now? -HOSHIO JUKUJOSKY MAEDA, EIKO USHIRODA
-什麼？妳現在才發現嗎？ -（前田朱庫久蘇奇星雄，牛路田）
You certainly will do anything people ask.
左藤真的大都是有求必應
Sato, give me your panties.
左藤，可以把內褲給我嗎？
You're the worst.
你很差勁耶
-Your mom's. -Mom's?!
-妳媽媽的 -居然是要媽媽的？
You're the worst.
不管怎樣，你都差勁到不行
-Uh, sure! -You're okay with that?
-這個嘛…好啊 -居然答應了？
You have to say no!
該拒絕的時候就要堅決說不！
-Um, but I guess panties are okay. -It's not okay!
-不過只是內褲而已，應該還好 -一點都不好！
Let's practice saying no.
那我們現在來練習拒絕別人
I'll ask you, and you say no. Okay?
我隨便拜託妳一些事，妳要說不喔
Okay!
好啊
Hey, my parents are in debt.
跟妳說，我爸媽在外面欠了一筆債
Can you lend me 100,000 yen?
妳可以借我十萬圓嗎？
What? I-I'll do my best!
什麼？我會努力湊錢的！
For you, Eiko!
為了幫助妳，影子！
Say no! I'm glad you would, though.
就跟妳說要拒絕啦！ 雖然妳這樣說我很高興
Alright, how about your granny's panties?
那給我妳奶奶的內褲
You're still stuck on that? That's disgusting!
你還在想這件事啊？噁心死了！
-Sure… -No!
-好啊… -不行！
Being kind to people makes me feel good!
可是對別人好，自己心情也會很好啊
That's why I can't say no.
所以我總覺得無法拒絕
Your great-grandmother…
左藤，妳的曾祖母還活著…
If you keep doing what people ask, you're going to get scammed!
妳老是這樣來者不拒 總有一天會受騙上當的
If you're too soft, everyone else will get soft too…
而且妳太寵著別人 也會讓對方變成廢人…
-Sure! -I'm still talking!
-好啊 -我話還沒說完！
Am I too soft?
我算是老好人嗎？
You there, sorry! Hold the corner of this poster!
那位同學，不好意思 幫我按住海報的邊角！
Certainly!
好啊！
Anyway, what made them think I'm too much of a pushover?
話說回來，為什麼我會對 “有求必應”這件事產生懷疑呢？
Thanks!
謝謝妳！
Whoa!
哇！
Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
Oh, thanks.
喔，謝謝妳
Taking that to the staff room?
是要拿去教職員辦公室的嗎？
I'll carry it for you.
我幫你拿過去吧
Huh? No, I'm alright. It's pretty heavy.
什麼？不用啦，這還滿重的
No, it's fine! I'm totally fine.
不用客氣啦，完全沒問題
Uh. Hang on.
啊，等一下
Komi, if you need anything, just ask!
古見同學，妳有什麼事需要幫忙 也可以跟我說喔
WOBBLE
（搖晃）
Whoa.
哇
SLIDE
（拿起）
Y-You too, Sato.
左藤同學，妳也是…
IF YOU NEED ANYTHING, JUST ASK.
（如果妳有什麼需要幫忙的 也可以跟我說）
You can't take it all.
不用全拿啦
I'll take half and you two can take the rest.
我拿一半，另外一半妳們兩位分就好
-I guess I'll carry some too. -CLASS VICE-PRESIDENT
-真拿你們沒辦法，我也來幫忙吧 -（副班長）
You should be helping already.
你本來就應該要幫忙拿
Thanks, Sato and Komi, for the help!
謝謝妳們，左藤同學、古見同學 幸好有妳們幫忙
What about me?
那我呢？
Yeah, yeah. Thanks.
好啦，也謝謝你啦
IF YOU NEED ANYTHING, JUST ASK.
（如果妳有什麼需要幫忙的 也可以跟我說）
Now that I think about it.
這麼說來
I've never asked anyone for help.
我好像從來沒有請別人幫忙過
Um, Komi?
那個，古見同學
I, uh…
我啊…
Every morning, I clean the classroom.
每天早上都會來教室打掃
Um, uh…
就是會…
I wipe off the desks and set them straight.
擦擦桌子，把桌椅排整齊之類的
So anyway, um…
所以我想說的是…
Asking for help is so stressful!
原來請人幫忙會這麼緊張！
If you don't mind…
如果妳方便的話
Do you think you could help me?
可以請妳一起來幫忙嗎？
-Whoa, what am I saying? -HIDING BEHIND AN "X" OF HAIR
-不對！我在講什麼啊？ -（秘技，鬢髮X字遮羞術）
If I need help, I should just quit!
妳應該覺得“既然需要人幫忙 那就別做這種事”對吧？
Sorry, I'm acting weird.
對不起，突然說這種奇怪的話！
T-Thank…
謝謝妳…
I'll help too!
我也要來幫忙！
I didn't know you were doing that!
原來妳一直在幫大家打掃啊？
I'd love to help you as well.
請務必讓我一起幫忙
After that,
在那之後
Morning cleaning became a daily activity for Grade 1 Class 1.
晨間打掃變成 一年一班的每日例行公事
MISSION 74 "IT'S JUST A FIGHT."
（任務74 吵架了）
Komi wants to ask what she's reading, but she can't.
古見同學想問她在看什麼，但不敢問
-FELT HER GAZE -What's up, Komi?
-（感受到了視線） -怎麼了嗎？古見同學
Oh, this?
喔，這個嗎？
It's a shogi puzzle book.
這是解將棋殘局的書
Do you want to try?
古見同學，妳要來解解看嗎？
She's really interested in trying shogi puzzles.
沒想到她會對將棋殘局這麼感興趣！
It's so cute!
好可愛！
Tadano! How about some shogi puzzles?
只野同學要不要一起來玩將棋殘局？
-W-What's that? -KATO THE PUSHY AUNT
-什麼東西？ -（變為多事大嬸的加藤同學）
PUZZLES BY SETSUJITSU FUKUI
（《將棋殘局》 福井誠實著）
Here's a puzzle I made. I won't say how many steps to checkmate.
這個是我設計的殘局題目 先不跟你們說走幾步會將死喔
Yes, that's the first move. And next is…
對，第一步這樣走沒錯，那下一步…
Oh, this is great!
天啊，真是太棒了！
Communication via shogi!
透過將棋來溝通
All people, connecting through the miracle of the board.
無論男女老幼 都能在棋盤上交流的奇蹟！
Shogi is the best!
將棋最棒了！
Huh? No. Why take it with the pawn?
什麼？不對吧，為什麼要用“步”？
Why not go with the rook?
走“飛車”不就好了嗎？
If you use a pawn…
走“步”的話
It'll come back, right?
還是要再退回來
If you go here, then here, there's no point!
像這樣，這樣不是很沒意義嗎？
Uh… huh?
奇怪
So if you use the rook, you can do it in five…
就跟妳說，只要用“飛車” 五步就能結束了…
Hm? No no no.
等一下，妳這不對吧？
You've got to move it.
這個時候應該要這樣走
I told you, you're wrong.
妳那樣不對啦
Um…
那個…
Oh! C-Class is starting!
啊！要上課了！
GLOOMY
（悶悶不樂）
They were tense.
悶悶不樂的兩人
CLASS IS OVER
（下課了）
Hey, listen!
你們兩個聽我說！
At a factory in my neighborhood, this guy…
之前我家附近工地有個大叔…
Hm? What's wrong?
什麼？你們怎麼了？
Nothing?
沒有啊
Huh?
怎麼了？
Since when were you two close enough to fight?
你們兩個什麼時候 感情好到會吵架了啊？
They blushed.
他們害羞了
BONUS SCENE
（片尾彩蛋）
What Tadano said would go like this, then this.
只野同學所想的棋路是這樣
And the gold general would stop it.
在這裡會被“金”擋住
Oh, is that right!
啊，對耶！
I was only thinking about the king.
我剛剛滿腦子只想著“玉將”的走法
Sorry to you too, Komi. I jumped to conclu…
古見同學，對不起，是我太武斷了…
SMUG
（得意）
Komi's smug face was cute, too.
（一臉得意的古見同學也好可愛）
EXTRA BONUS SCENE
（附加片尾彩蛋）
I brought Komi and Tadano!
我帶古見同學和只野同學過來了！
Oh, welcome!
喔，歡迎你們！
I think you already know Ushiroda.
我想你們都知道了，這位是牛路田
I'm in the seat behind you, but we've never really talked.
我坐在比較後面的位子 很少跟你們說到話
This is Maeda. His seat is in front of yours, Komi.
這位是前田同學 是坐在古見同學前面的位子吧
Komi, is your grandmother still alive…
請問古見同學的奶奶還活著…
73 people left to reach 100 friends.
距離交100個朋友，還剩73人
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：林琬清